Guide to the Leo Stein Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1910-1950; Series III; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - WRITINGS OF LEO STEIN
    - Dewey. Quest for Certainty, holograph notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 216)
    - Distortion, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 217)
    - [Education, some thoughts on], typescript corrected, [1910?] (Box 10, Folder 218)
    - Identity and Object, typescript, annotated (Box 10, Folder 219)
    - Integrity and Integration, printed version, The New Republic, 1926 Apr 7 (Box 10, Folder 220)
    - [Introduction to exhibition of paintings by Robert Hallowell], printed versions, 1925 (Box 10, Folder 221)
    - Journey Into the Self
      - [Anecdote printed in Journey Into the Self ], holograph fragments, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 222)
      - [typescript of letter about Gertrude Stein printed in Journey Into the Self ], n.d. (Box 10, Folder 223)
      - [typescript of letters from LS to Mabel Foote Weeks printed in Journey Into the Self ?], 1910, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 224)
      - Reviews, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 225)
    - Judgments of Taste and Judgements of the Agreeable, typescript, corrected (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - Knowing and Feeling, printed versions, corrected, unidentified publications, 1926 Mar 17 (Box 10, Folder 227)
    - [Lecture for the New School for Social Research?], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 228)
    - [Lecture I at the New School for Social Research?], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 229)
    - [Lecture II at the New School for Social Research?], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 230)
      Includes: flyers and announcement
    - Mabel Dodge Hodge Podge, holograph, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 231)
    - Masterpieces [and related chapters], holograph, corrected (Box 10, Folder 232)
    - Meanings [or Art and the Modern World], printed version with notes, unidentified publications, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 233)
    - [Monuments, letter on], holograph, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - Norman Douglas, D.H. Lawrence, and M.M., typescript, corrected (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - A Note on Art [Introduction to a catalogue of an exhibition of paintings by Edward Bruce], printed version, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 236)
    - On Present Discontents, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 237)
    - On Teaching Art and Letters, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1926 Mar 3 (Box 11, Folder 238)
    - The Painting of Arthur B. Davies, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1918 Jan 19 (Box 11, Folder 239)
    - Personality and Identification, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1926 Mar 31 (Box 11, Folder 240)
    - Poems, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 241)
    - Poetry and Prose, typescript, corrected (Box 11, Folder 242)
    - Practice--Nirvana, Chapter II, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 243)
    - The Primitive and the Grotesque [introduction to an exhibition catalogue by Annette Rosenshine], 1925 (Box 11, Folder 244)
      Includes: clippings and photographs of sculptures
    - Psychology Art and Betting, typescript fragment (Box 11, Folder 245)
    - Radio Talk--Mr. Leo Stein, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 11, Folder 246)
    - Rembrandt's Etchings in the Public Library, printed version, corrected, 1918 Mar 2 (Box 11, Folder 247)
    - Renoir, typescript carbon, corrected [in French], n.d. (Box 11, Folder 248)
    - Renoir and the Impressionists, printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1929 Mar 30 (Box 11, Folder 249)
    - Review of Aesthetic Experiences by Lawrence Buermeyer, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 250)
    - Review of Aesthetic Experiences by Lawrence Buermeyer, printed verision, The New Republic, 1926 Mar 17 (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - Review of "Beyond Architecture," printed version, corrected, Journal of the American Institute of Architects, ca. 1918 (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - The Revolt of the Poets, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 253)
    - Rhythm and Affirmation, holograph (Box 11, Folder 254)
    - Ritual and Reality, draft [titled Enlightenment and Integration], typescript carbon, corrected (Box 11, Folder 255)
    - Ritual and Reality, printed version, corrected, The American Scholar, 1947 Spring (Box 11, Folder 256)
    - Ritual and Reality, offprints from The American Scholar, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 257)
    - Ritual and Reality, proof of letter to the editor by Frank Pierce Jones, The American Scholar, 1947 Apr 16 (Box 11, Folder 258)
    - The Seesaw of Sympathy, typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 259)
    - Sex fundamentals, holograph fragment (Box 11, Folder 260)
    - Snob into Society, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 261)
    - Tradition and Art, printed version, The Arts, 1925 May (Box 11, Folder 262)
    - Truth and Civilization, typescript (Box 11, Folder 263)
    - [Wells, H.G.], typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 264)
    - William James, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 265)
    - William James and the Individual [letter to the editor], printed version, corrected, The New Republic, 1926 Sep 15 (Box 11, Folder 266)
    - Zuloaga, printed version, The New Republic, 1916 Dec 23 (Box 11, Folder 267)
    - Untitled, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 268-294)
    - Untitled, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 295-324)
    - Fragments, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 325-328)
    - Wrappers, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 329)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Aiken, Conrad, "A Basis for Criticism," printed version, The New Republic, 1923 Apr 11 (Box 12, Folder 330)
    - Aldred, Anderson, "Divisations", typescript corrected (Box 12, Folder 331)
    - Besson, George, "Renoir à Cagnes," printed version in unidentified publication, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 332)
    - Corneau, Eugène, "L'Exposition Coubine à la Galerie Bernheim-Jeune," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 333)
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, essays, 1925-26, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 334)
      Includes: "Gurdjieff Says," typescript, corrected; Intimate Memories forword, typescript, corrected, "Native Air," printed version, The New Republic; "Tension & Morality," typescript
    - Stein, Nina, manuscripts, typescript and holograph (Box 12, Folder 335)
    - Weeks, Mabel F., forward to Journey into the Self, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 336)
    - unidentified holograph fragment [re: Renoir], n.d. (Box 12, Folder 337)
    - Poems by unidentified, 1943-44 (Box 12, Folder 338)
- Personal Papers, 1898-1946; Series IV; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series IV, Personal Papers, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Clippings
    - Bruce, Edward, 1929-30, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 339)
    - Stein, Gertrude, 1933-46 (Box 13, Folder 340-341)
      [collected by Leo Stein, including 2 annotated by LS?, printed copies of "American" series by GS, and exhibit catalog containing "Introduction to the catalogue of an exhibition in London of Sir Francis Rose's pictures"]
    - Stein, Leo, 1927-47 (Box 13, Folder 342)
  - Diploma--Johns Hopkins University, 1898 Jun 14 (Box 13, Folder 343)
  - Exhibition Catalog: Edward Bruce, 1929 (Box 13, Folder 344)
  - Exhibition Catalog: Models for a Monument to the Pioneer Woman, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 345)
  - Exhibition Catalog: Leo Stein paintings, Società Leonardo da Vinci, Florence [posthumous], n.d. (Box 13, Folder 346)
  - Inventories and Receipts for artwork by Otakar Coubine, 1928-32, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 347)
  - New Republic [mentioning Gertrude Stein], 1922 Nov 29 (Box 13, Folder 348)
  - Power of attorney documents by Nina Stein for Howard Gans, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 349)
- Photographs, 1910-1947; Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  Series V, Photographs, is arranged alphabetically.
  - Friends (Box 14, Folder 350)
    Includes: Mr. and Mrs. Edward Bruce, Rudolf Levy, and [Renoir?]
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 351-352)
    Series of photographs picturing Mabel Dodge Luhan's home in Taos, along with scenes of New Mexico and Arizona.
  - Paintings, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 353-355)
    Artworks by Edward Bruce and by [Henri Matisse?]
  - Places, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 356)
    Includes 27 Rue de Fleurus and unidentified hilltop city
  - Stein, Leo, 1927-28, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 357)
  - Stein, Leo and Nina - snapshots, 1914, 1922, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 358)
  - Stein, Leo and Nina - series in Settignano, ca. 1946-47 (Box 14, Folder 359)
  - Stein, Leo - with friends (Box 14, Folder 360)
    Includes: Mr. and Mrs. Edward Bruce, Otakar Coubine, and Rudolf Levy
  - Stein, Nina, 1910?, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 361)
  - Unidentified (woman reading book and two poses of woman with young boy)
    See: Oversize, Box 22, folder 500
- Artwork by Leo Stein, n.d.; Series VI; 12; (7 boxes)
  Series VI, Artwork by Leo Stein, is organized into sections by format or subject. Works are listed according to the order assigned by the 1980 Yale Art Gallery survey, except for the Cone and Keck gifts, which are listed in the order received. The oil paintings on canvas were removed from their stretchers and are stored flat in folders.
  - FIGURE SKETCHES
    - Pencil and watercolor sketches (Box 15, Folder 362)
  - OIL PAINTINGS ON CANVAS
    - [Nude woman seated on bed], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 363)
    - [Flowers in vase], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 364)
    - [Nude on stool], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 365)
      [on edge of canvas: "nu assis en toilette"]
    - [Nude with flower], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 366)
      [on edge of canvas: "nu à la rose"]
    - [Nude (Suzanne)], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 367)
    - [Vase of flowers], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 368)
    - [Vase of flowers], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 369)
    - [Vase of flowers], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 370)
    - [Standing nude] (Box bsd, folder 371)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 372)
    - [Still life - vase with flowers], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 373)
    - [Head of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 374)
      [on edge of canvas: "tete de femme"]
    - [Street scene], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 375)
    - [Landscape] (Box bsd, folder 376)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 377)
      [on edge of canvas: "femme et étoffe"]
    - [Still life with fruit], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 378)
    - [Standing nude - rear view] (Box 15, Folder 379)
    - [Still life], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 380)
    - [Sleeping nude], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 381)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 382)
    - [Seated man with cane], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 383)
      [on edge of canvas: "vieux assis"]
    - [Standing nude] (Box bsd, folder 384)
    - [Seated woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 385)
      [on edge of woman: "Anne"]
    - [Seated woman reading], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 386)
      [on edge of painting: "femme assise, jupe noir, vu au dos"]
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 387)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 388)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 389)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 390)
    - [Vase with flowers - still life], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 391)
    - [Still life], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 392)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 15, Folder 393)
    - [Seated man], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 394)
    - [Street scene], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 395)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 396)
    - [Still life with bust and statuette] (Box bsd, folder 397)
    - [Landscape] (Box bsd, folder 398)
    - [Landscape] (Box bsd, folder 399)
    - [Landscape] (Box 15, Folder 400)
    - [Landscape] (Box bsd, folder 401)
    - [Landscape] (Box bsd, folder 402)
    - [Portrait of old man], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 403)
    - [Portrait of old man], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 404)
    - [Portrait of old man], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 405)
    - [Portrait of woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 406)
    - [Portrait of woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 407)
    - [Portrait of woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 408)
    - [Portrait of woman (nude)], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 409)
    - [Portrait of seated woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 410)
    - [Portrait of woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 411)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 412)
    - [Standing nude] (Box bsd, folder 413)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 414)
    - [Standing nude] (Box bsd, folder 415)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 416)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 417)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 418)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 419)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 420)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 421)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 422)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 423)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 424)
    - [Seated woman], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 425)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 426)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 427)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 428)
    - [Standing nude] (Box bsd, folder 429)
    - [Standing nude (male)] (Box bsd, folder 430)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 431)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 432)
    - [Seated nude], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 433)
    - [Two nudes], n.d. (Box bsd, folder 434)
    - [Nine small paintings: 7 landscapes, 1 head of a woman, and 1 vase on a table] (Box 16, Folder 435-436)
  - OIL PAINTINGS ON BOARD
    - [Landscape] (Box 16, Folder 437)
    - [Seated woman], n.d. (Box 16, Folder 438)
    - [Seated woman], n.d. (Box 16, Folder 439)
    - [Seated woman], n.d. (Box 16, Folder 440)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 441)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 442)
    - [Landscapes] (Box 17, Folder 443)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 444)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 445)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 446)
    - [Landscapes] (Box 17, Folder 447)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 448)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 449)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 450)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 451)
    - [Landscape] (Box 17, Folder 452)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 453)
    - [Still Life], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 454)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 455)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 456)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 457)
    - [Still life with fruit and statuette] (Box 17, Folder 458)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 459)
    - [Reclining nude], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 460)
    - [Portrait of a woman], n.d. (Box 17, Folder 461)
  - NOTEBOOK SKETCHES
    - Pencil sketches of landscapes and figures (Box 18, Folder 462-476)
  - OIL ON BOARD FROM THE COLLECTION OF MRS. JULIUS W. CONE
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 477)
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 478)
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 479)
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 480)
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 481)
    - [Landscape] (Box 19, Folder 482)
  - OIL ON BOARD FROM THE COLLECTION OF MRS. SHELDON KECK
    - [Head of a woman], n.d. (Box 20, Folder 483)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 484)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 485)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 486)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 487)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 488)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 489)
    - [Landscape] (Box 20, Folder 490)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 491)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 492)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 493)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 494)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 495)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 496)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 497)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 498)
    - [Landscape] (Box 21, Folder 499)
- Oversize, n.d.; 1.5; (1 box)
  Oversize contains one item from Series V.
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Unidentified (woman reading book and two poses of woman with young boy) (Box 22, Folder 500)